Hey בוקר טוב, Boker tov, חודש טוב, Chodesh tov, we're in the
lead up now to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, one month to go.
Actually, there'll be a reference to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in today's
דף. Daf. Today's דף Daf is מ"ז, Mem Zayin, and we pick
up at the very bottom of מ"ו עמוד ב', Mem Vav Amud
Beis, literally the last line, three words from the end. And the
current discussion is the משנה Mishna asks the question כיצד מפרישין חלה
בטומאה. Keitzad mafrishin challah b'tumah. Hey בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
How you take חלה challah from a טמא tamei dough on dough
on the יום טוב Yom Tov of פסח Pesach where you're sort
of in a bind because you can't bake it because you're not
going to eat it, it's טמא חלה. tamei challah. You can't not
bake it because it'll become חמץ. chametz. You can't burn it because
you can't burn things unnecessarily on יום טוב. Yom Tov. What do
you do? So, three-way debate in the משנה, Mishna, whether you put
it in cold water so it doesn't ferment, whether you don't have
to worry about it at all because it's חלה, challah, so it's
קודש, kodesh, it's not yours, it's the כהן's, Kohen nobody transgresses, whether
you bake it before you call it חלה challah and then you
call it חלה, challah, multiple loaves and then you pick one and
make it חלה challah after it's been baked. So, we'll get back
to that, but to sort of give us the necessary background, the
גמרא Gemara here's in the middle of a heated debate between רבא
Rava and רב חסדא Rav Chisda about if somebody bakes on יום
טוב Yom Tov for the weekday whether one actually gets lashes. It
would seem that you should. It's not the allowance of אוכל נפש
ochel nefesh because you're not doing it for the purpose of יום
טוב Yom Tov and nevertheless רבא Rava says theoretically you could eat
it on יום טוב Yom Tov even if that wasn't your
intent, הואיל, ho'il, theoretically since that if guests would drop by, now
you have made food. So it's a type of a cooking that
could serve the purposes of יום טוב Yom Tov even if it
wasn't your intent. And רב חסדא Rav Chisda says no, it has
to specifically be your intent, you would get lashes. How then can
you cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת? Shabbos? With an
עירוב תבשילין, Erev Tavshilin, he says that's because שבת Shabbos you're allowed
to cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת. Shabbos. The problem
is cooking from יום טוב Yom Tov to the weekday. And if
you did that and that was your intent, no matter what hypotheticals
there are, you would get lashes. So the גמרא Gemara continues with
this debate. Last line on the bottom מ"ו עמוד ב'. Mem Vav
Amud Beis.
איתיבי, Eisivai, I'll ask you, says רבא Rava to רב חסדא. Rav
Chisda. לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, we have a ברייתא Braisa that says
that the showbread, the bread they would put on the שולחן Shulchan
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, which they would bake, they would
replace every שבת. Shabbos. So it would sit on the table for
the week and they'd eat it the following שבת. Shabbos. So the
ברייתא Braisa teaches נאכל לתשעה, ne'echal l'tishah, it could be eaten on
day nine from the day it was baked, לעשרה l'asarah day ten,
ולאחד עשר u'l'achad asar or on day eleven from the day it
was baked. לא פחות ולא יותר, Lo pachas v'lo yoseir, not more
and not less than nine, not more than eleven. כיצד, Keitzad, how
would you get these three possibilities?
כדרכו, K'darko, if it was a normal week, לתשעה, l'tishah, it would
be eaten on day nine. נאפה בערב שבת, Ne'efah b'erev Shabbos, it
would be baked on Friday and נאכל בשבת, ne'echal b'Shabbos, it would
be eaten on the following שבת, Shabbos, which you might say that's
eight days but it's nine because if you give each day a
number, what happened to my marker? Here we go. Right? So if
this
is our calendar,
right? So this is Sunday and this is Friday and this is
שבת, Shabbos, okay? So if it was baked on Friday and then
it was replaced on שבת Shabbos with last week's bread,
so then it would be eaten on day nine. The following שבת
Shabbos would be considered as day nine from the day if you
count one for the day it was baked. That would be on
a normal שבת. Shabbos. Baked on day one, replaced ערב שבת, erev
Shabbos, replaced on day two, eaten the following שבת Shabbos on day
nine. Okay. חל יום טוב להיות ערב שבת, Chal Yom Tov l'hiyot
erev Shabbos, if Friday was a יום טוב, Yom Tov, נאכל לשבת
לעשרה. ne'echal l'Shabbos l'asarah. So then it would be eaten on day
ten, right? Because it's obviously you
don't
bake the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim on שבת. Shabbos.
I'm very sorry to ask this, would you just in one to
two sentences just repeat the problem?
No problem, we're just describing, well, we'll turn, you don't bake the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim on שבת. Shabbos. You replace it on שבת
Shabbos and you eat it a week later. So if you're going
to replace it on this שבת Shabbos and you're going to eat
it on this שבת, Shabbos, when do you bake the new לחם
הפנים? Lechem HaPanim? So in a normal day you bake it on
ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. You're not going to bake on שבת, Shabbos,
right? It's not like a קרבן korban that has to be done
today, it has to be baked today or whatever, so you bake
it here. If this day is יום טוב, Yom Tov, this is
going to be the relevant of the crux, the assumption is you
can't bake it on this day יום טוב Yom Tov to be
eaten a week later on that שבת, Shabbos, so you'll bake it
here and then you'll replace it on שבת Shabbos and it will
wind up being day ten. Okay? Is that clear? All right. Yes?
But can't you, I mean, is there no dispensation for baking it
because it's needed in the מקדש? Mikdash?
Right, so the answer is no, because it didn't have to be
done that day. If there was, if you had to do it,
then you could do, like you bring a קרבן Korban that day,
but since there's no need, you could not.
But isn't it, you're talking about when it was eaten, it was
stale?
The לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, that was one of the miracles, it
didn't get stale.
Okay, so now, נאכל לעשרה, ne'echal l'asara, that's ten days. Now, נאכל
לאחד עשר. ne'echal l'echad asar.
שני ימים טובים של ראש השנה, Shnei yamim tovim shel Rosh Hashanah,
if however Friday and Thursday were the first two days of ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, it's very appropriate for ראש חודש אלול, Rosh Chodesh
Elul, then נאכל לאחד עשר, ne'echal l'echad asar, it would be eaten
the following שבת Shabbos on eleven. So if Friday and שבת Shabbos
were day one and two of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, it would
have to be made on,
if actually Thursday and Friday were day one and two of ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so it would have to be made on Wednesday,
you exchange it on שבת Shabbos and you eat it on day
eleven. Now the problem with that is, the problem with that is,
what's the problem with that? Is that in that scenario,
yeah, who said that? יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So if this was
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
right, so,
okay, so it would be eaten on the eleven. Now the eleven
is the day after, the day after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right?
It's actually, yes, right, because if these are whatever, I'm sorry, right,
no, wait, did I do that wrong? I did that wrong. Not
Wednesday, I knew something was wrong. Right, right, right, it's baked on
Wednesday, sorry, exactly, exactly, that's the problem.
Right, right, right.
Okay, five and five. Right, this, this is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
so it can't be baked on Wednesday, on, on Thursday, so it's
baked here, okay, but the problem, so here's where you bake it,
right, so it's day eleven from the day it was baked, but
that would be day ten of תשרי, Tishrei, right? Because if this
is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
so how
are you eating it on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur?
Yeah, you understand the problem?
Right, it's baked on this, which is day eleven from the day
it was baked, right,
but that's יום כיפור Yom Kippur if that's ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
So the answer is, so רש"י Rashi asks that question. The answer
is that for us, right, like today is a perfect example, today
is ראש חודש אלול. Rosh Chodesh Elul. What day is number one
of אלול? Elul? Tomorrow, right? Today is actually day, you know, thirty,
right, of אב. Av. So on a two day, on a two
day ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, it's the second one which is usually
the actual first of the month. ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is only
the exception the way we've set up the calendar where you have
a two day ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh that the first one is
day one. But in the time of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
if you would have a two day ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, actually
why would you have a two day ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in
the time of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, not the way we've
set up the calendar? Because the עדים eidim came later than מנחה,
Mincha, right? And therefore, because they came later than מנחה, Mincha, you
say we can't accept you for today, come back tomorrow, but we'll
treat the rest of today as if it was ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, right? But as if it was ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. But
actually we would actually, this would be day one of תשרי, Tishrei,
it would be like any normal
two
day ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh where the second day would actually be
number day one of תשרי. Tishrei. So in this scenario, they wouldn't
bake it on either day, they'd bake it here, but this would
be one of תשרי Tishrei and you'd wind up eating it on
ערב יום כיפור, Erev Yom Kippur, not on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
In those scenarios where the עדים eidim came after מנחה, Mincha, so
they retroactively treated it as if it were ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh,
let's say,
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right?
They continued to treat, what did they do, the regular קרבנות, korbanos,
they didn't
offer?
Right. No, yes, but I don't want to get, you know, too
much detail, that we'll get to later. Okay, but the only point
here is, is that in this scenario, it would be eaten on
day, it could be baked here, eaten on day eleven, day eleven
is not יום כיפור Yom Kippur because in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash in this scenario תשרי Tishrei one is Friday, not Thursday, the
same way by a normal two day ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
But you're only baking it on Wednesday because you anticipate that maybe
עדים eidim will come tomorrow.
Exactly, exactly. That's a good point too, when you baked it on
Wednesday, you didn't know, right, why you needed, and in a way
you could say if you're here on Wednesday, you could say we
don't need to bake it today, if the עדים eidim come on
Thursday. No, then bake it on Friday. If עדים edim don't come
on Thursday, we'll bake it on Thursday. So the only reason you're
baking it here is because you're afraid of the scenario where they'll
come מן המנחה ולמעלה, min hamencha u'lemala, which is a good point.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara now continues. So that's the scenario.
Now, why is this relevant to two things?
You're afraid they'll come at the break of dawn and you won't
have time to
bake it.
Right. No, then bake it on Friday.
So why would you have to bake it?
The only reason you'd bake it on Wednesday is you'd be afraid
they come מן המנחה ולמעלה. min hamencha u'lemala.
So make Thursday morning?
Before they come? Bake it at noon?
No, you wouldn't bake it Thursday morning because then you'd be afraid
they'd come early and it would turn out to be ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah.
Then you would bake it tomorrow.
But then
you can't bake
it, when are you going to bake it? You can't bake it
Thursday morning because they might come in any minute now and it'll
be ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So you don't bake it Thursday morning.
Got it. So then we'll have to wait till Friday.
But then if they came Thursday morning, so you'd stop baking, you'd
bake it Friday.
Yes, but if you already baked and they came, you would retroactively
have violated ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
Oh, but now we don't
say—I don't know, I don't know. Okay, apparently you baked it on
Wednesday to play it safe. All right, so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
לפי, lephi, so the ברייתא Baraita continues, שאינה דוחה לא את השבת
ולא את יום טוב, she-eina dokha lo et ha-Shabbat v'lo et Yom
Tov, because you don't violate שבת Shabbat or יום טוב Yom Tov
to bake the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Now, ואי אמרת ve-i amarta
says רבה, Rabba, if you'd say צרכי שבת נעשין ביום טוב, tzorkhei
Shabbat na'asin be-Yom Tov, you רב חסדא Rav Chisda says that the
reason you can cook from שבת Shabbat to יום טוב Yom Tov
is because you're allowed to fundamentally cook from יום טוב—I Yom Tov
mean, you can cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת, Shabbat,
you're fundamentally allowed to cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת.
Shabbat. אמאי לא דחי יום טוב? Amai lo dakhi Yom Tov? So
why not? Meaning he says, look, I don't get it. Forget the
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah scenario. Whatever the case is, why not cook
even if this is יום טוב, Yom Tov, cook here for the
following שבת? Shabbat? Meaning I say the reason you can cook from
יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת Shabbat is fundamentally צרכי חול נעשין
ביום טוב. tzorkhei chol na'asin be-Yom Tov. Okay, but you say the
reason
is—I mean, not צרכי חול נעשין ביום טוב. tzorkhei chol na'asin be-Yom
Tov. I say fundamentally it is because of הואיל. ho'il. Now, okay,
this a little maybe a little confusing, but let me try to
explain this. Okay, if this day is יום טוב, Yom Tov, right,
the ברייתא Baraita says you can't cook on it. Okay, now, if
רבה Rabba says, I have an explanation why you can't cook on
this יום טוב Yom Tov for the following שבת. Shabbat. Why do
I say in a normal יום טוב Yom Tov you're allowed to
cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת? Shabbat? So my reason,
says רבה, Rabba, is הואיל. ho'il. הואיל ho'il is theoretically guests could
come and theoretically you could wind up eating it today. When you
if you were to cook the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim on this
Friday, could I say—bake it—could I say theoretically you could wind up
eating it today? No, it's לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. You're not allowed
to eat it till the next week. So I know why you
can't cook on יום טוב Yom Tov for שבת. Shabbat. There's no
theoretical way you could eat it today. But you רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, you say the reason you're allowed to cook from יום טוב
Yom Tov to שבת Shabbat is not because theoretically you're allowed to
eat it today, but because you have a license to cook from
יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת. Shabbat. You're allowed to cook from
יום טוב, Yom Tov, not because theoretically it could be eaten today.
So if you're allowed to cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to
שבת, Shabbat, cook from Friday to the following שבת, Shabbat, assuming that
it's not because we see it as one big יום טוב, Yom
Tov, but that even if it's a distant שבת, Shabbat, you're fundamentally
allowed to. So why not cook from Friday to a week later?
Isn't that only when you couldn't have cooked it beforehand?
What? Are you allowed to cook, you know, in anyway?
I don't know, we don't say that by עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin
you have to have been able to cook it beforehand.
No, meaning like there's one thing—it's going to
if you're going to cook it for like a שבת Shabbat well
in advance, what's the point of דוקא davka specifically making it on
יום טוב?
Yom Tov? I don't know. Why not—yeah, so say the same, forget
all of your עירוב תבשילין, eruv tavshilin, cook a day before. We
don't say that.
You still should have had fresh food, but לחם הפנים lechem hapanim
is going to be for a week anyway. All right, so what's
the difference? So cook it a day early.
So what? And if it's so it's a day old, if you
normally cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת, Shabbat, make it
two days old. Obviously that's not an issue. They're allowed to do
it. So let's see what he says. So אמר ליה, amar lei,
he says back to him, שבות קרובה התירו שבות רחוקה לא התירו.
shvut krovah hitiru shvut rehokah lo hitiru.
No. Because I normally hold that there is a שבות, shvut, a
rabbinic problem. I say biblically you're allowed to cook from יום טוב
Yom Tov to שבת, Shabbat, rabbinically you're not. So when did we
allow you with an עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin or whatever to cook
from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת? Shabbat? Remember we said yesterday
that's a rabbinic problem. That's when it's right next to it, it's
juxtaposed. If it's going to be a long time afterwards, that they
didn't allow. So basically the point is no here it's different, it's
a long time away. But he doesn't say that that's a biblical
problem. Fundamentally you're right. I hold that there's a principle that you're
allowed to cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת. Shabbat. It
could be a שבת Shabbat a year later. But you're doing it
for a purpose of a שבת, Shabbat, that's allowed. But rabbinically we'll
only allow it when it's the next day, not when it's a
week later. What's the difference? So you could say the simplest thing
you could say is that remember we said the purpose of the
עירוב תבשילין eruv tavshilin according to some is you don't come to
make a mistake and think you're allowed to cook from יום טוב
Yom Tov to חול. chol. So we could say if you're cooking
for the next day and the next day is שבת Shabbat and
you're making an עירוב תבשילין, eruv tavshilin, it's obvious that it's a
special allowance. allowance for שבת, Shabbat, you won't come to cook from
יום טוב Yom Tov to חול. Chol. If you're cooking for eight
days later, there's no it's not obvious today when you're cooking what
purpose you're cooking for. Now you could say what do you mean?
The בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you're cooking לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim, what
other purpose would you cook it for? But nevertheless, in principle, it's
a lot less obvious when it's so far in the distance. And
therefore, even though biblically you're right, you'd be allowed, rabbinically you would
not. You could also reframe it in a more fundamental way which
I would prefer to say, which would be that rabbinically we would
like to do it when it's an expansion of the one day,
when it's all one big, you know, it's when the days are
juxtaposed so it becomes like an extended יום טוב. Yom Tov. When
there's a break in time, that right, you know, exactly, well not
because of the freshness issue, but just because when there's a break
in time, it's less it's less as if you're cooking it for
the you know for the day you're in the middle of. So
that what he says is in principle you're right. I mean, I
would have said this distinction even at a biblical level. In principle
you're right. I feel you can't cook for tomorrow, you don't say
the principle of theoretically you could eat it today, but you have
a license to cook on יום טוב Yom Tov for שבת, Shabbat,
but rabbinically we won't allow that if it's not the next day,
if it's so far in advance. Either because then you'll come to
cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to חול Chol or because then
it's not like an extended יום טוב Yom Tov and we're only
going to allow it rabbinically when it's an extended יום טוב. Yom
Tov.
So the justification for the license to cook from יום טוב Yom
Tov to שבת Shabbos in this particular position is that it's קודש
לקודש? Kodesh l'Kodesh?
Yes, that's it in particular.
And that the חול Chol in between
would not make a difference? Now I agree with you, I would
have said that that should be a biblical difference, that יום טוב
Yom Tov to חול Chol is not just oh there's some justification
because it's for a legitimate purpose, but that it's considered like an
extended קדושה Kedusha and it's all for today, you know, an extended
idea of what today is, like we say it's a three day
יום טוב. Yom Tov. We don't say it's a two day יום
טוב Yom Tov followed by a one day שבת, Shabbos, right? Conceptually
it all becomes one big thing. It's קודש. Kodesh. Yeah, so you
could I would have said that biblically, but the גמרא Gemara is
here assuming no, biblically, technically you would be allowed to do it.
Maybe you could even cook from פסח Pesach to סוכות, Succos, you
know, who knows? But rabbinically you need it to be all all
one extended period. Okay, so let's see now what the גמרא Gemara
says.
So שבות קרובה התירו, Shvus krovah hitiru, when it's a rabbinic thing
for an immediate following day they allow it. שבות רחוקה לא התירו,
Shvus rechoka lo hitiru, not for a distant time. ולרבן גמליאל U'l'Rabban
Gamliel says the גמרא, Gemara, according to...
and then we have אין שבות
במקדש.
Ein
shvus b'Mikdash.
Right, so אין שבות Ein shvus just waives the need for doing
an עירוב תבשילין, Eiruv Tavshilin, which does not sort of, as רש"י
Rashi says, does it would not sort of say if it's a
fundamental thing that we want to protect, you know, right, we would
sometimes draw the line. Okay. ולרבן גמליאל דאמר משום רבי שמעון בן
הסגן. U'l'Rabban Gamliel d'amar mishum Rabi Shimon ben ha-Sgan. According to רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that says in the name of רבי שמעון בן
הסגן Rabi Shimon ben ha-Sgan in another place, but he discusses this
exact case: דוחה את יום טוב ואינה דוחה יום הצום. Doche es
Yom Tov v'eina doche Yom ha-Tzom. He actually says you're allowed to
bake לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim on יום טוב Yom Tov for a
שבת Shabbos a week long a week
later. So this was a סגן הכהנים? Sgan ha-Kohanim? What?
So this was a סגן הכהנים? Sgan ha-Kohanim? Presumably he would know.
Well, if it ever happened, right, and then it becomes an interesting
question about historical evidence within a halachic debate. But you would not
bake לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim on יום כיפור Yom Kippur for a
שבת. Shabbos. Same way you wouldn't bake it on שבת Shabbos for
a שבת Shabbos later, but you would bake it on יום טוב
Yom Tov for a later שבת, Shabbos, even a שבת Shabbos a
week later. So according to him, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar?
How do you explain it? Meaning what's the logic of that position
if you just said they didn't allow it when it was distant?
So that's like a softball question. בהא פליגי, B'ha palgi, this is
what they debate. מר סבר שבות קרובה התירו שבות רחוקה לא התירו.
Mar savar shvus krovah hitiru, shvus rechoka lo hitiru. One says when
did they allow you to cook from יום טוב Yom Tov to
שבת Shabbos only if it was the following day. ומר סבר, U'mar
savar, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds, שבות רחוקה נמי התירו, shvus rechoka
nami hitiru, they even allowed you to cook for שבת Shabbos a
week later. Okay, so here you have it. רבא Rava says, according
to me, the problem of cooking on יום טוב Yom Tov for
following שבת Shabbos is I only allow you to cook on יום
טוב Yom Tov if theoretically it's edible today, and לחם הפנים Lechem
Hapanim is not theoretically edible today, you can't eat it for a
week. But you, רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, you say you have a
license to bake from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת, Shabbos, cook
from יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת, Shabbos, why not? And he
says you're right, it's a rabbinic problem, I don't allow it when
it's so far in the distance, and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would
not be concerned about that rabbinic problem. But fundamentally you do have
this license even if it's a week later. Okay,
now, the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב רב מרי, Mesiv Rav
Mari, so רב מרי Rav Mari asks the following question from another
ברייתא. Braisa. שתי הלחם אינם נאכלות לא פחות משנים ולא יותר על
על שלשה. Shtei ha-lechem einam ne'echalos lo pachos mishnayim v'lo yoseir al
shlosha. The שתי הלחם Shtei ha-lechem that you would bring on שבועות,
Shavuos, same idea, you would have to bake them ערב שבועות. Erev
Shavuos. Now that's a little bit less clear why you'd have to
bake them on ערב שבועות, Erev Shavuos, right? שבועות Shavuos is יום
טוב Yom Tov and you're going to eat them on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, so why not bake them on יום טוב? Yom Tov?
So that's actually a little bit curious, so we'll get back to
that in a minute. The כהנים Kohanim eats those? The כהנים, Kohanim,
right. לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim also. Yes.
Are they considered תרומה Terumah or it's a separate category?
No, it's considered a type of a קרבן. Korban. Yes, exactly. Okay,
so the
שתי הלחם... Shtei ha-lechem... would be eaten no fewer than two days
on the day... from the day it was baked, counting, you know,
the
endpoint. Meaning it would be baked on ערב יום טוב Erev Yom
Tov and eaten on יום טוב. Yom Tov. ולא יותר על שלושה,
V'lo yoter al shlosha, not more than three. כיצד? Keitzad? How? נאפות
ערב יום טוב. Ne'efot Erev Yom Tov. In a normal case it
would be baked ערב שבועות. Erev Shavuot. נאכלות ביום טוב, Ne'echalot b'Yom
Tov, eaten on שבועות, Shavuot, that's day two, לשניים, Lishnayim, day two.
חל יום טוב להיות אחר השבת, Chal Yom Tov l'hiyot achar HaShabbat,
if יום טוב Yom Tov followed שבת... Shabbat... you can't get ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah in here, it's שבועות. Shavuot. Okay, so, but if
שבת Shabbos is, if שבועות Shavuos was on
Sunday, so שבת Shabbos preceded it. נאכלות ליום טוב לשלושה, Ne'echalot l'Yom
Tov lishlosha, be eaten on day three, right? Because it would be
baked on... on Thursday, and then it would... you would hold it
around on Friday, and then you would bring it on שבת Shabbat
on... on...
did I say that wrong? It would be baked on
Friday. You would do nothing on שבת. Shabbos. And then it would
be brought on Sunday, which would be day three. Okay, so that's
לשלושה. Lishlosha. לפי שאינו דוחה לא את השבת ולא את יום טוב.
Lefi she'eino doche lo et HaShabbat v'lo et Yom Tov. You don't...
you can't cook it on שבת Shabbos or יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Now, we obviously understand why you don't bake it on שבת. Shabbat.
But why don't you bake it on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Is
an important question anybody has to ask that issue. So רש"י Rashi
says there's a whole long תוספות Tosafot and whatever. I'll just give
you רש"י's Rashi explanation. רש"י's Rashi basic explanation is that according to
רבה's Rabba principle that you can only bake on יום טוב Yom
Tov because in theory... you're allowed to bake on יום טוב Yom
Tov even for... for the next day, because in theory it could
be eaten now. He says when you bake the לחם הפנים, Lechem
HaPanim, when you take it out of the oven, in theory it
cannot be eaten now even if you were to bake it on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why not? Because you would still have to
שחט shacht and bring the קרבן. Korban. So therefore, at the time
that you were baking, it is not theoretically edible now, and if
you never bring the קרבן Korban today, you'll never be able to
eat it now. So therefore, according to רבה, Rabba, רבה Rabba says
that's why I say you can't bake it on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. But according to you, if you could bake it even for
a distant שבת Shabbat in principle, it doesn't have to have the
ability to be eaten now. It just has to have that justifying
reason that you're doing it for the sake of a שבת. Shabbat.
Well then certainly, if you're doing it for later in the day
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, even if you need to bring the
קרבן Korban in between, that barrier should not be an issue for
you. For me, רבה Rabba says, I have the stringency that I
need it to be able to be eaten now. That's why it
didn't bother me why you can't bake לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim for
a week later, you're not able to eat it now. Now, with
that leniency, I throw in a... a leniency that I don't care
what you're thinking in your head, as long as hypothetically you could
eat it now, that's enough. Okay, but at least you have to
hypothetically be able to eat it now. That's not true by לחם
הפנים Lechem HaPanim and it's not true by שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem.
You can't hypothetically eat it now, you still have to go through
a process of bringing a קרבן. Korban. But you don't say hypothetically
you have to eat it now. You care what's going on in
that guy's head. But for you it's okay as long as you're
planning on doing it for the sake of a שבת. Shabbat. So
if you can even a distant שבת, Shabbat, so certainly if you're
planning on doing it for later on the day of יום טוב,
Yom Tov, even if you still have to get over the hurdle
of a קרבן, Korban, the fact that you're planning on doing it
for later on the day of יום טוב Yom Tov should be
enough of a justification. Let's read it and then I'll take your
questions. So he says like this, ואי אמרת, V'ee amrat, if you
say צרכי שבת נעשין ביום טוב, Tzorchei Shabbat na'asin b'Yom Tov, fundamentally
you could do something from יום טוב Yom Tov to the שבת
Shabbat that's future, it doesn't have to be theoretically edible now. השתא
דשבת ביום טוב שרי, Hashta d'Shabbat b'Yom Tov shari, if you can
do something on יום טוב Yom Tov for the purpose of a
שבת, Shabbat, even in principle a distant
שבת, Shabbat, דיום טוב ביום טוב מיבעיא, D'Yom Tov b'Yom Tov mibaya,
how much more so could you do something on יום טוב Yom
Tov for later in the יום טוב, Yom Tov, even if there's
a barrier of first having to bring the קרבן? Korban? That's the
way רש"י Rashi means it. גמרא's Gemara answer is no, שאני התם
דאמר קרא לכם. Shani hatam d'amar kra lachem. The reason you can't
do that is because the תורה Torah says אך אשר יאכל לכל
נפש הוא לבדו יעשה לכם, ach asher ye'achel l'chol nefesh hu levado
ye'aseh lachem, that you have to bake it for your purpose. לכם
ולא לגבוה. Lachem v'lo l'Gavoha.
Only if you're baking it for your purpose, not if you're baking
it for the purpose of a קרבן. Korban. Now, that's just an
exception that even though eventually you'll wind up eating it, if fundamentally
it's a type of you're eating משולחן גבוה mishulchan Gavoha and you're
not eating because it's your food, but it's brought for God and
you just indirectly benefit. It's sort of like the debate of בית
שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל Beit Hillel and the whole questions
about bringing שלמים Shlamim on יום טוב. Yom Tov. You'll wind up
eating all of the meat, but fundamentally it's an act of bringing
a קרבן. Korban. It's not an act of preparing food for you
to eat. So here too, he says yes, you know, normally you'd
be able to do it for a distant שבת, Shabbat, for this,
for that, but this is an act of bringing a קרבן. Korban.
It's not an act of making food for you to eat. Now,
in theory maybe you could have answered used that answer for the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim as well, for the earlier question, but okay,
this is the answer we came to now. So one minute. So
he says that's why you can't. So yes, generally you have a
license, but not when it's fundamentally the act of bringing a קרבן.
Korban. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל דאמר משום רבי שמעון בן הסגן דוחה
את יום טוב מאי איכא למימר? V'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel d'amar mishum
Rabi Shimon ben HaSgan doche et Yom Tov, mai ika l'meimar? However,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that would say actually,
the same way before, he said you could bake the לחם... Lechem...
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim on יום טוב Yom Tov for a distant
שבת, Shabbat, here he would say you could bake the שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem on שבועות Shavuot for שבועות. Shavuot. So what's the argument
for that? You know, whatever happened to the whole idea of לכם,
lachem, you're doing it not, you're doing it, you know, you have
to do it for your purpose, not for the קרבן korban purpose.
So סבר לה כאבא שאול, savar leh k'Abba Shaul, he holds like
אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, דאמר de'amar לכם, lachem, what does לכם lachem
come to exclude on יום טוב? Yom Tov? לכם ולא לנכרים, lachem
velo lenochrim, that you can't do it for non-Jews. For God, especially
A, that's considered a very elevated purpose and maybe also B, in
time you're going to wind up eating it anyway. So indirectly it
is for you. Like I said, there's a famous debate about בית
שמאי Beit Shammai בית הלל Beit Hillel goes through the whole thing
about bringing שלמים Shelamim on יום טוב. Yom Tov. You'll wind up
eating all of the meat, but the basic act is first of
that of bringing a קרבן. korban. The eating of the meat is
only a derivative type of thing. So here too you could say
fundamentally it's bringing a קרבן, korban, your benefit is secondary, and therefore
that would be debated. Some would say that's okay, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, the חכמים Chachamim would say it's not
okay. And that's what's going on here. Maybe you could have said
that's also the issue about the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim and in
principle, yes, I still hold by my position. You can cook on
יום טוב Yom Tov for a following שבת, Shabbat, you have a
license to do it. It doesn't have to be theoretically edible now.
In theory you should be able to cook on שבועות Shavuot for
שבועות Shavuot later in the day, even if there's some obstruction in
the middle like the need to bring a קרבן. korban. The problems
here are specifically that you can't do a cooking or a baking
or whatever that's for the sake of a קרבן. korban. It has
to fundamentally be for your purposes. Okay? And the other position that
holds it's okay says we're only excluding doing it for the sake
of non-Jews, people that are, you know, it's you're not eating, somebody
else is, and that other person isn't a Jew, so it's not
within that basic license of cooking on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And
that's the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
that says actually cooking as a קרבן korban if you're going to
wind up eating is actually okay.
Let me turn to the first position. The first position that doesn't...
the first position holds from הואיל ho'il you're saying?
Position of רבה Rabbah holds from הואיל. ho'il. I don't care what
you're planning, what you're thinking. You could be thinking that you're going
to eat it in a week from now. As long as it
is theoretically edible now.
But he's not given to guests though. That whole thing is הואיל
ואי בעי, ho'il ee ba'ei, it's the same thing as the לחם
הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, right?
Yeah, but that means the guest could drop in any second.
But there are no guests with the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem.
Because exactly right. That's why he says that's exactly why I don't
have a problem why you can't do it on שבת... Shabbat... why
you can't do the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim on יום טוב Yom
Tov and why I say you can't do the שתי הלחם Shtei
HaLechem on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Exactly for that reason, there's no
way you can eat it now. You or a guest or anybody
could eat it now.
But for guests though doesn't mean that I have to be able
to eat it, it means that the guests could be... yeah... yeah...
cause in other words I could still not be able to eat
it. Like let's say, like for instance let's say I'm cooking something
and I'm in a תענית Taanit or something and I'm פליישייג fleishig
or something.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It doesn't make a difference. It just means that
theoretically it's edible now. Correct.
Well, you could have argued the opposite with the same principle. You
could say חציו לכם וחציו להשם. chatzi lachem chatzi l'Shem. הקדוש ברוך
הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu is your guest.
Wow, that might be רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel.
I'm not sure if it's based on the לכם lachem principle but
לכם ולהשם. lachem va'Shem. But yes.
The assumption is, I'm sorry to say I don't remember from קדשים,
Kodashim, but the assumption is when does the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
that you're baking become קדש? kodesh? Right.
So when
you're baking it?
Yeah, so that's a good... you don't... yeah... I can't believe you
can't remember that... anyway, I mean there's a state where it becomes
קדש kodesh when it's being baked and then the כלי שרת, klei
shares, but it gets the full קדושה kedusha when the קרבן korban
is שחט. shechted. So it's sort of in stages. So you're right,
if it wasn't קדש kodesh at all, you could say I'll bake
it now and maybe I'll just wind up eating it now. I
won't make it part of the קרבן. korban. But in a way
you're caught in between. It's קדש kodesh enough that you can't eat
it now, but it's not fully reached its sort of level that,
you know, it can't be... it can't be eaten until the קרבן
korban is brought. It's enough קדש kodesh that you can't detach it
from the קרבן, korban, but it's not enough to finish the process
that you can eat it until the קרבן korban is brought. Okay,
so that's the debate. So רבה Rabbah in the end again says
I get all these things because I say you have to be
able to eat it now. You say you don't have to be
able to eat it now, you say but intent matters. So according
to you what's the problem here if you have a license for
שבת Shabbat and for יום טוב Yom Tov and so on? And
the thing is, this is special, it's a קרבן, korban, there's rabbinic
issues, etc. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
so far רבה Rabbah has gotten in his licks, right? He's asked
all the hard questions. Now we're going to have רב חסדא Rav
Chisda try to get challenge רבה. Rabbah. So שלח ליה רב חסדא
לרבה, shelach leh Rav Chisda le'Rabbah, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda sent
to רבה Rabbah the following challenge to רבה, Rabbah, ביד רב אחא
בר רב הונא. biyad Rav Acha bar Rav Huna. He sort of
sent the following challenge in the hands of רב אחא בר רב
הונא. Rav Acha bar Rav Huna. So apparently they were having like,
you know, people that play like what is it like correspondence chess.
You know, this was a debate that wasn't necessarily going online. They
had a long-standing debate. So at one stage רב חסדא Rav Chisda
has, oh you're going to see רבה? Rabbah? I got a good
question for him. Challenge him with this. So here's the question he
gave רב אחא בר רב הונא Rav Acha bar Rav Huna to
challenge רבה Rabbah with. מי אמרינן הואיל, mi amrinan ho'il, do we
say your principle of "since" hypothetically you could eat it today and
that's enough? והתנן, ve'hatnan, we have the following משנה. Mishna. יש חורש
תלם אחד, yesh choresh telem echad, a person can make one furrow
in a... yard
and transgress eight prohibitions. This is in מכות Makkos which speaks about
giving lashes and has like a fun up thing about where this
often comes up in a discussion about eating one type of a
bug and getting five lashes but speaks about how many different sort
of prohibitions right לאוין lavin can we pile on into one action.
Right so you get like it was a fun little exercise they
did. Okay so here's the משנה Mishnah says you can get eight
things from making one furrow. What are the eight things? החורש בשור
וחמור, Hachoresh beshor vachamor, you're ploughing with an ox and a donkey
together so that's number one לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור יחדו Lo tacharosh
beshor uvachamor yachdav והן מוקדשים vehein mukdashim they are sanctified so you're
transgressing the prohibition of מעילה me'ilah which is two. רש"י Rashi says
and number three רש"י Rashi says there's a specific prohibition of actually
doing עבודה avodah with קרבנות korbanos קדשים. kodashim. So the שור shor
this is the way רש"י Rashi reads it תוספות Tosafos has a
different version. The ox is a real קדושת קרבן kedushas korban it
could be brought as a קרבן korban so that's the prohibition of
doing עבודה avodah with a קרבן. korban. וחמור Vachamor is not a
קרבן korban but it could still be sanctified for its value בדק
הבית. bedek habayis. So that's number three that's מעילה. me'ilah. That's how
רש"י Rashi gets that's three for רש"י Rashi וכלאים בכרם vekilayim becherem
and what they happen to be ploughing in is grape grape seeds
and and wheat together that's four. תוספות Tosafos actually has says that
the מעילה me'ilah and the עבודה avodah with קרבן korban he conflates
that into one and he gets another one cause he says there's
two prohibitions. It's both כלאי זרעים kilay zerayim and כלאי הכרם. kilay
hakerem. Okay so there's two different it's wheat barley and and grape
seed according to תוספות. Tosafos. Anyway by now we've got four. ושביעית
Veshvi'is it happens to be a שמיטה shemittah year. ביום טוב Beyom
tov and it's יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay so you're now ploughing
on יום טוב Yom Tov we're up to six. וכהן ונזיר בבית
הטומאה Vechohein venazir beveit hatumah and you happen to be doing it
in a graveyard and you're כהן kohein and a נזיר. nazir. Okay
and another כהן kohein or נזיר? nazir? No and a נזיר. nazir.
That gives you seven and eight. Of course the last two seemed
a little cheap because the last two wasn't the act of ploughing
it was just you happened to be in a vineyard at least
the first six were the act of ploughing per se. Anyway those
are your eight. ואי אמרינן Ve'im amrinan if you say הואיל ho'il
that on יום טוב Yom Tov you get out of cooking on
יום טוב Yom Tov even if you did it לצורך חול letzorech
chol because hypothetically you could be eaten now. So אחרישא לא ליחייב
acharesha lo litchayev you shouldn't be חייב chayav for ploughing on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. Why? דחזי לכיסוי דם ציפור Dechazi lechisuy dam tzippor
because you could maybe maybe theoretically you have a legitimate purpose for
that for that ploughing. You could use the dirt to cover the
blood of a שחיטה shechitah of a chicken. Now okay so you
weren't expecting guests that day? No guests were around you in your
farmhouse nobody was coming. Okay no but to me it's a very
strange question because
he
understands רבא Rava and that רבא's Rava saying look you could do
a real מלאכה melachah on יום טוב Yom Tov but if I
could give you a hypothetical scenario where that would be allowed then
I can't give you lashes. Okay and if he says oh then
even if you ploughed or תוספות Tosafos says how about if you
did any single מלאכה melachah on שבת Shabbos or יום טוב Yom
Tov hypothetically there could be a חולה שיש בו סכנה choleh sheyesh
bo sakanah
which doesn't seem to be רבא's Rava point. רבא's Rava point seemed
to be cooking is explicitly מותר mutar right. It's not that in
theory there could be a case the תורה Torah allows you to
cook allows you to do food preparation. The point is though it
has to be לצורך יום טוב. letzorech yom tov. So I say
the hypothetical possibility is enough to make it לצורך. letzorech. That's very
different from something which the way it is is a direct violation
it's a type of thing that's not allowed on יום טוב Yom
Tov and you can give me a completely alternate scenario in which
it might be allowed. It's very different than the act of cooking.
By the way I should even say that you know we almost
take this for granted because it's a major issue on יום טוב
Yom Tov how much justification you need for something. Does something have
to be eating like or does or some things basically almost blanket
permitted. We have in our head and it's based on certain גמרות
Gemaras but it's actually debated in the ראשונים Rishonim that two things
are basically fundamentally totally permitted on יום טוב Yom Tov two מלאכות
melachos which ones? Carrying and a fire.
Right right cooking we no but
you might sort of say before you actually cook you we would
treat making a fire as more blanket permitted ironically than the act
of cooking. Act of cooking we say we need some justification. But
if I'm carrying something without an עירוב eiruv I don't think like
oh one minute do I have a good enough justification to be
carrying? Right or if I'm putting lighting something like I'm lighting a
יארצייט yahrzeit light or something like that you know oh wait minute
is that really enough of a justification to do it? Now actually
based on certain סוגיות sugyos in the גמרא Gemara you might actually
need a good justification but the point I'm making though is is
that we know in our head it's not just like everything is
equally forbidden but if you have this thing that's a מתיר. mattir.
And we know that there are certain things on יום טוב Yom
Tov that are more. or in principle blanketly allowed, okay? And therefore,
it seems that what רבא Rava is saying is that cooking fundamentally
is permitted, okay, as long as hypothetically it could whatever. That's very
different than an act of plowing, which is fundamentally forbidden. Okay, that
seems to be the real answer, but nevertheless רב חסדא Rav Chisda
did understand him that way. And רב חסדא Rav Chisda understood you
could do a real מלאכה melacha and as long as I could
give you a scenario that it would be allowed, that should get
you off the hook for lashes. So why not say that even
if you really plow? So we'll see what the answer is, but
I do have to ask another question, which is, and why if
I was plowing in order to get the dirt to cover the
blood of a chicken, why would that be okay on יום טוב?
Yom Tov? Right? I mean, it's not needed in order to eat
the chicken, it's just a separate מצוה. mitzvah. So what would you
say? Like עשה דוחה לא תעשה? asei doche lo ta'asei? So תוספות
Tosfos says, but יום טוב Yom Tov is a לא תעשה lo
ta'asei and an עשה. asei. So why does the גמרא Gemara even
assume that you could plow
even that scenario in itself is allowed? Since when can you plow
to get dirt to cover the blood? The first משנה, mishna, what's
the first משנה mishna in ביצה? Beitzah? Right? It's about the having
the shovel and the ashes and the loose dirt because you're not
allowed to do that stuff to cover the blood of a chicken
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So תוספות Tosfos has a whole long
discussion figuring that out. I will just put that out there as
a,
what's the answer? There's not a straightforward answer. Okay, so let's keep
on reading. So it seems like a very bizarre question. A, since
when is it allowed to do for the sake of the blood?
And B, that wasn't really what רבא Rava was saying. But let's
see what the גמרא Gemara answers. So אמר רב פפא בר שמואל,
amar Rav Papa bar Shmuel, so notice by the way we didn't
hear רבא's Rava's answer. We're going to hear other people answering for
רבא. Rava. I would wager that if רבא Rava were to answer,
he would say what we said. He would say, give me a
break, it's not cooking, I was talking about cooking. Okay, but let's
see what other people say. So says רב פפא בר שמואל, Rav
Papa bar Shmuel, בבני מכורזלוות. bevani mekurzalot.
We're talking about that what you're plowing is like hard clumps of
earth. So therefore, when you're plowing, you can't use those clumps to
do כיסוי הדם, kisoy hadam, because it's not loose dirt. So that's
the case. In principle, if it was loose dirt, you're right, you
wouldn't get lashes, but it's talking about these hardened clumps. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ראויות לכתוש. reu'yos lekotsan. Oh big deal, so you
could grind them up and still use it for covering the dirt.
So the גמרא Gemara says, וכתישה ביום טוב מי שרי? vechtisha beYom
Tov mi shari? No, you can't do that. You can't grind up
dirt on יום טוב. Yom Tov. תוספות Tosfos says and you also
can't plow dirt on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So if you can
plow in order to get the dirt for כיסוי הדם, kisoy hadam,
why is it assuming that you can't grind it up in order
to get it for כיסוי הדם? kisoy hadam? It's a very bizarre
גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says that's not an answer. So
the גמרא Gemara says fine.
ראויות לכתוש כלאחר יד. reu'yos lekotsan k'la'achar yad. No, you can still
grind it up with a שינוי. shinui. So you can't tell me,
oh you can't use it for כיסוי. kisoy. You could still use
it even if it was a hardened clump you could grind it
up. So the גמרא Gemara says בצינמא. bitzunma. Fine, we're talking about
actual rocks. What you're doing is you're plowing through rocks and therefore
you can't use it for
כיסוי הדם. kisoy hadam. So the
גמרא Gemara says, צינמא בר זריעה? tsunma bar zeri'ah? So the גמרא
Gemara says, one minute, if you're plowing through rocks, how are you
doing everything else there? How are you plowing כלאים kilayim and שביעית?
shevi'is? You can't plant anything if you're plowing through rocks. So the
גמרא Gemara says, צינמא מלמעלה ועפר תיחוח מלמטה. tsunma mil'ala v'afara tichucha
mil'mata. Fine, there's rocks at the top layer and there's dirt below.
And that's why you're plowing in order to plant in the dirt
below. גמרא Gemara says, oh there's dirt below. So it says ותיפוק
ליה משום עפר תיחוח. v'tippok lei mishum afarta tichucha. So you're getting
to the dirt below. So that dirt you could use for כיסוי
הדם. kisoy hadam. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר מר בר
רב אשי Ella amar Mar bar Rav Ashi בטינא. bitina. טינא tina
which is like a very like muddy dirt. So it's enough that
you have to plow to make a furrow to plant, but it's
not soft and loose and therefore, and even, and there's no way
you can make it usable for covering and for כיסוי הדם. kisoy
hadam. So this has got to be the most bizarre question. Again,
because for us the answer is obvious. רבא Rava is saying I
don't say you could do מלאכות melachos and get out of it
because of a hypothetical. I say you could do cooking on יום
טוב Yom Tov and cooking on יום טוב Yom Tov is always
okay because in theory it could be edible. But he understood רבא
Rava more broadly. He asked him about this case of plowing. And
at least the answers were given were these hypothetical cases, or these
not these hypothetical but these special cases where you can't use it
for כיסוי הדם. kisoy hadam. And as we said, what's not even
clear is even if you could use it for כיסוי הדם, kisoy
hadam, how does that allow it on יום טוב? Yom Tov? Since
when are you allowed to plow on יום טוב Yom Tov in
order to do כיסוי הדם? kisoy hadam?
It seems like by the time you got to the generation of
רב פפא, Rav Papa, of רב פפא Rav Papa at least as
a דעת יחיד da'at yachid understood this to be a more general
principle.
I know, he bought into רב חסדא's Rav Chisda's question. You know
at least he was, you know, taken in by רב חסדא's Rav
Chisda's question and assumed, bought into the assumption of the question. You
know, sometimes, you know, the first mistake you make is by responding.
You know, it's the... question of like, you know, what's that thing
like, you know, it's said in a very harsh way, like, you
know, what is it like, you know, if somebody like, what have
you stopped beating your wife? Like you can't answer the question, right?
'Cause you've already lost as soon as you buy into the assumption
of the question.
So, so, I know, I gotta come up with a less, a
less disgusting example than that. But that's the... anyway, but you can't
say, so if you answer, as soon as you're answering רב חסדא,
Rav Chisda, you're buying into his assumption. So at least that's what
these אמוראים Amoraim assumed, yes.
So the first opinion was just coming back to basics. דאורייתא D'Oraisa
שחיטה shechita נעשית ביום טוב na'aseis b'yom tov and the reason why
we have to have an עירוב תבשילין Eruv Tavshilin is that it's
okay to cook,
right? What about the other side? Well, you didn't explain why he
needed
same principle that, oh, the גמרא Gemara says it, the גמרא Gemara
in ביצה Beitzah discusses it, it's because of like כבוד יום טוב
Kovod Yom Tov and you shouldn't wind up doing all your preparations
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. זלזול. Zilzel. זלזול, Zilzel, exactly. Okay. That's
how you address it, or?
No. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says, oh, I'm sorry, I ended a minute too soon. ותינא
בר זריעה היא? V'tina bar zri'a hee? So, oh, I'm sorry, so
תינא tina first was like a type of a, of like a
plaster. So the גמרא Gemara says you can't plant in that. So
fine. במסונתא. B'masunta. במסונתא B'masunta was finally the muddy dirt that you
can plant in it but you can't use it for כיסוי הדם.
Kisui HaDam. Okay. איתיביה אביי, Eisivei Abaye, אביי Abaye asked, המבשל גיד
הנשה, Ha'mevashel gid hanasheh, it's gonna be the same type of question,
and now we're no longer with רב Rav and רב חסדא. Rav
Chisda. People are sort of bought into רב חסדא'ס Rav Chisda's line
of questioning and give answers buying into his assumption and ask further
questions buying into his assumption. So אביי Abaye is now gonna jump
on this bandwagon. And we have another משנה Mishna that says, or
ברייתא, Braitah, that says המבשל גיד הנשה בחלב ביום טוב ואוכלו לוקה
חמש. Ha'mevashel gid hanasheh b'chalav b'yom tov v'ochlo lokeh chameish. You cook
גיד הנשה gid hanasheh in milk on יום טוב Yom Tov and
you eat it, you get five lashes. Okay. Why? Cooking because you're
cooking
on
יום טוב Yom Tov for something you're not allowed to eat, so
it's cooking
לא לצורך. lo l'tzorech. You're, it's גיד, gid, you're חייב chayiv for
cooking a גיד הנשה בחלב. gid hanasheh b'chalav. This assumes that a
גיד gid is treated like meat, so it's בשר בחלב. basar b'chalav.
Okay. You ate, you ate גיד הנשה gid hanasheh with חלב, chalav,
so you ate a גיד הנשה gid hanasheh and you ate בשר
בחלב, basar b'chalav, that's two more. And where's number five? Oh, it's
gonna say, משום מבשל גיד ביום טוב. mishum mevashel gid b'yom tov.
So you cooked on
יום טוב Yom Tov without צורך. tzorech. לוקה משום מבשל גיד ביום
טוב ומשום אוכל גיד ומשום מבשל בשר בחלב ומשום אוכל בשר בחלב
ומשום הבערה. Lokeh mishum mevashel gid b'yom tov u'mishum ochel gid u'mishum
mevashel basar b'chalav u'mishum ochel basar b'chalav u'mishum havarah. Oh, and for
making the fire.
And then you'd say what about הואיל וחזי ליה? ho'il v'hazee lei?
Okay.
Well, the גמרא Gemara will say something like that. ואם אמרינן הואיל,
V'im amrinan ho'il, if you say הואיל, ho'il, so you can't say
הואיל ho'il that I could have eaten this גיד gid because you
could never have eaten this גיד. gid. But say הואיל ho'il on
the
fire. הבערה לא ליחייב הואיל וחזי ליה לצורכו. Havarah lo l'chayeiv ho'il
v'hazee lei l'tzorecho. Don't get lashes for the fire because you could
use the fire for other purposes. Now this to us makes a
lot more sense than the plowing, because we already have bought into
the idea that the things that have a basic license on יום
טוב Yom Tov are fire, carrying, and to a lesser, interesting, ironically,
to a lesser degree cooking. So if רבא's Rava gonna say as
long as you're cooking it's okay because hypothetically it could be used
on יום טוב, Yom Tov, he should certainly say the same about
a fire. Even if you made the fire for the purpose of
cooking this גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, theoretically this fire is usable. Why
do you get lashes for a fire? Which for us is a
very good question, because it would never occur to us to think
you could make a fire on יום טוב Yom Tov and get
lashes, for whatever reason you made it. So why here should you
get lashes? It should be just like the cooking question.
But first of all, I just wanna clarify, is he talking about
igniting a fire or transferring? Igni...
well, no, I would say that the difference between igniting and transferring
is a rabbinic difference. Rabbinically you cannot make a new fire because
it is labor intensive and it's something new and there's special reasons.
But in terms of the biblical מלאכה, melachah, it makes absolutely no
difference if it's a new fire or transferring. And we take it
for granted that once you're not igniting a fire you have a
complete license, there's no problem of the מלאכה melachah of a fire.
But that's not the starting point of the גמרא. Gemara. The starting
point of the גמרא Gemara is that this is a מלאכה. melachah.
And then it's right, if רבא Rava uses a הואיל ho'il principle
to give you more latitude by cooking, then as far as we
know he should certainly use that principle to give you more latitude
by a fire. So how could you be חייב chayiv for making
a fire?
So really conceptually there actually is no difference between the example of
הבערה havarah and חורש, choresh, it's only cultural that we are not
agricultural, we're not farmers. It doesn't make sense to us. But the
underlying...
No, I wouldn't say it's cultural. I would say that the הלכה
halachah based on this and other גמרות Gemaras actually developed that there
actually is a more blanket license by, I would say, by carrying
and by fire, and to some degree by cooking. But the גמרא
Gemara is treating them all the same. By the way, while once
we're talking about it, it's interesting to note, like, I get somewhat
fire because it's related to cooking, although I should have just as
much of a license in the cooking מלאכה. melachah. as I showed
in the fire מלאכות, melachos, so that’s great. But carrying? Why is
carrying there such a license? And it’s interesting to note that the
fire and the carry and the cooking and the carrying are the
two מלאכות melachos that are somewhat most unique on שבת Shabbat in
the sense that, I don’t know if most unique is a word,
that carrying is what the ראשונים Rishonim call a מלאכה גרועה. melacha
grua. It’s a weak מלאכה, melacha, weak not in the sense that
you’re not violating and it’s and it’s a capital crime and all
that, but it’s the only non-productive מלאכה, melacha, non-creative מלאכה. melacha. And
fire is the only one mentioned explicit in the תורה. Torah. לא
תבערו אש בכל משבתיכם Lo tivaru esh bechol moshvoseichem and there’s actually
an opinion of the תנאים Tannaim that even if you make a
fire on שבת, Shabbos, it’s only a לאו lav and you’re not
חייב מיתה, chayav misa, that it’s ללאו יצאה. lav yatza. So those
two already have a more questionable status. And come יום טוב Yom
Tov and they get a more blanket allowance. And cooking gets a
pretty much of a blanket, not a total, but a much more
of a of a free of of you know of of a
license because it’s אך אשר יעשה לכל נפש. ach asher yeiaseh lechol
nefesh. So for us it’s not just cultural. Actually halachically, fire, carrying,
and cooking have are מלאכות melachos that have much more of a
blanket allowance on יום טוב Yom Tov than other מלאכות. melachos. But
this גמרא Gemara isn’t treating it that way. And this גמרא Gemara
says if you used הואיל ho'il for cooking, you should use it
for plowing. But at least here we can more relate to the
question based on how we know the הלכה halacha of יום טוב
Yom Tov and says if you’re going to use הואיל ho'il to
give you license for cooking, you should you should be using it
to give you license for making a fire, which actually is what
we do. So how here are you giving this guy lashes for
making a fire? So let’s see what he
says. ואימא הואיל הבערה לא ליחייב הואיל דחזי ליה לצורכו, Ve'emayina ho'il
havara lo lichayiv ho'il dechazi lei letzurcho, you could use the fire
for your own purposes. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back
to him, you're right. איפכא הבערה ועייל גיד הנשה של נבילה. Eipcha
havara ve'ayeil gid hanasheh shel neveila. Let's switch the text of the
ברייתא. braisa. You can't you're not going to get lashes for for
making the fire. We'll we'll make the scenario that the גיד הנשה
gid hanasheh also happens to be of an animal that wasn't shechted
properly. So you'll get lashes, the fifth lashes will be for eating
נבילה. neveila. So you ate a גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, נבילה, neveila,
בשר בחלב. basar bechalav. Okay, all those three prohibitions wrapped into one.
Switch the גרסא. girsa. So the גמרא Gemara says והתני רבי חייא,
ve'hatani Rabbi Chiya, but רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught a ברייתא, braisa,
לוקין שתים על אכילתו ושלש על בישולו, lakin shtayim al achilaso veshalosh
al bishulo, two of the lashes are for eating and three are
for cooking. So that you can't switch the the the fire, which
is a cooking-related מלאכה, melacha, and turn it into eating נבילה, neveila,
because we have we've grouped them. There are two for eating, בשר
בחלב basar bechalav and גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh, and three related to
cooking. So we have to change if we're going to take out
making the fire we have to replace it with a מלאכה melacha
that is related to the act of cooking. So he says ואי
איתא, ve'isai, and according to you, שלש אכילתו מיבעי ליה, shalosh achilaso
mibaei lei, it would be three for eating, גיד הנשה, gid hanasheh,
בשר בחלב basar bechalav and נבילה. neveila. So if we're going to
take out fire it has to be replaced with something that's related
to cooking. So אלא איפכא הבערה, ella eipak havara, fine, take out
making a fire, you won't get lashes for that, ועייל עצי מוקצה.
ve'ayeil atzei muktza. What you did is, the problem was not that
you made a fire, but you made a fire with מוקצה muktza
wood. So, which is bizarre, since when is מוקצה muktza a biblical
issue? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ומוקצה דאורייתא הוא? vemuktza de'oraisa
hu? But I don’t understand since when is מוקצה muktza biblical that
you’re going to get lashes for using מוקצה? muktza? אמר ליה amar
lei אין, in, yes, דכתיב והיה ביום הששי והכינו את אשר יביאו.
dechisiv ve'haya bayom hashishi veheichinu es asher yoviu. Day six they will
prepare and this is you've learned ביצה, Beitzah, the beginning of ביצה
Beitzah there's הכנה דרבה, hachana deRabbah, which is understands that there's a
biblical idea of preparing the stuff. Now it's one thing to say
there's a biblical idea of preparing what you're going to use and
not using stuff that's מוקצה, muktza, but that you'll get lashes for
it? So ואזהרה מהכא, ve'haz'harah meihacha, and yeah, and here's why you'll
get lashes, מלא תעשה כל מלאכה. mi'lo sa'aseh kol melacha. So this
is like the crazy גמרא. Gemara. This גמרא Gemara says you'll get
lashes for using
מוקצה. muktza.
There's a biblical idea of מוקצה muktza and so much that it
becomes a מלאכה. melacha. Now, by the way, how does that solve
the problem? Why don’t we say הואיל? ho'il? If you could say
הואיל ho'il on making the fire, say הואיל ho'il on using מוקצה.
muktza. No, so the answer is no, because you could say הואיל
ho'il by a fire, a fire I could have a way that
I’m allowed to use it on יום טוב, Yom Tov, I make
a fire for a legitimate purpose, but if it’s the wood is
מוקצה, muktza, there’s no הואיל, ho'il, there’s no way there’s no legitimate
thing I can do with this on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
that’s the answer. Right, fire, that’s okay. מוקצה, muktza, oh, that’s the
problem.
But you need the wood for the fire, I understand, but it’s
מוקצה, muktza, there’s no license for this wood, to use this wood.
There’s no scenario you can use this wood if this wood is
מוקצה. muktza.
This is the only wood I have.
This is the wood you happened to use, and there’s no scenario
that you can use this wood. Okay, so that’s the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר ליה, amar lei, so that גמרא’s Gemara not going to be
happy with that, since when is מוקצה muktza I mean whatever, we
never say that מוקצה muktza goes so far to say that it’s
a מלאכה. melacha. So אמר ליה והא את הוא דאמרת, amar lei
ve'at hu de'amarta,
you’re the one who says בעי מיניה מרב חסדא, boei minei meiRav
Chisda, I asked רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, ואמרי לה בעי מיניה מרב
הונא, ve'amrei lei boei minei meiRav Huna, I asked רב הונא, Rav
Huna,
הביא צבי מאפר, heivi tzevi mei'afar, and slaughtered it תמיד tamid on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. and you wanted to bring it as a
קרבן תמיד Korban Tamid on יום טוב, Yom Tov, can you go
ahead and bring מוקצה muktzah because it's מוקצה muktzah was grazing out
in the wilderness, can you use a something מוקצה muktzah for a
קרבן? korban?
Did they check it like four days before?
What? All right, we won't worry about that. ואת אמרת לן ve'at
amarta lan and you said to us that here was the answer
you got that based on the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says
עולה olah and
ואמרת לן, ve'amarta lan, excuse me, you said about a שה. seh.
This is actually דרשונינג darshuning a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel that
speaks about a sheep ולא בכור. velo bechor. You can't bring a
קרבן korban from something that's already sanctified as a בכור. bechor. אחת,
achat, it's a שה אחת. seh achat. What pasuk is this?
It's a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. It says שה אחת מן
הצאן מן המאתים ממשקה ישראל. seh achat min hatzon min hamasayim mimashke
Yisrael. Okay, some פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. Okay,
so one sheep ולא מעשר, velo ma'aser, not מעשר ma'aser which is
one out of ten. Okay, you can't bring מעשר, ma'aser, an animal
that's מעשר ma'aser as a קרבן. korban. מן הצאן min hatzon from
the sheep ולא הפלגס. velo hapillegas. פלגס pillegas is an animal that
is no longer a שה seh but it's not yet an איל.
ayil. It's one year old, between one year and one year and
a month. Until one year it's a שה. seh. Once it hits
its one year birthday, it's basically a teenager. Okay, from one year
to a year and a month it's a teenager. When it's a
year and a month, then it's considered an adult and an איל.
ayil. So you can't bring a קרבן korban in this month after
its first birthday. מן המאתים min hamasayim from ממותר מאתים שנשתייר בבור.
mimutar masayim shenishtayer babor.
Now we're leaving the sheep and we're talking about wine. And if
you want to bring wine for a libation, you have to leave
over 200 in the well. What does that mean? This for this
is a principle, מכאן ערלה שבתלה במאתים. mikan orlah shebatlah bemasayim.
Again, these are this is really just a big אסמכתא, asmachta, a
lot of these things. But the point is, if you had some
unkosher wine, ערלה orlah wine, that got mixed up with your wine,
as long as there was 200 left over, it was one unit
to 200, it would be בטל. batel. So you could take the
wine of this mixture and if there were 200 other units left
behind, then the wine would be okay because it would be בטל.
batel. So again, it's a very, you know, אסמכתא asmachta learning to
apply to other principles of this principle of ביטול. bitul. But we're
getting to our point: ממשקה ישראל. mimashke Yisrael. The end of the
פסוק pasuk is, again, a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, from the
drinks of Israel. מן המותר לישראל. min hamutar leYisrael.
You can only bring קרבנות korbanot from things that are permissible to
be eaten, מותר באכילה. mutar be'achilah. מכאן אמרו אין מביאין נסכים מן
הטבל. mikan amru ein mevi'in nesachim min hatevel.
You can't use the wine, the same way you couldn't use wine
with ערלה orlah unless it had 200 and was בטל. batel. You
can't use wine if it's טבל. tevel. You can't bring as a
קרבן korban something that is otherwise forbidden to be eaten. Now here's
our upshot. יכול לא יביא מן המוקצה? yakhol lo yavi min hamuktzah?
Maybe you can't bring from an animal that's מוקצה? muktzah? Like the
sheep that was grazing in the wilderness. אמרת, amarta, no. מה טבל
מיוחד שאיסור גופו גרם לו? mah tevel meyuchad she'issur gufo geram lo?
The only thing that's forbidden is something like טבל tevel which is
intrinsically forbidden. אף כל שאיסור גופו גרם לו. af kol she'issur gufo
geram lo. Only something else that you can't bring as a קרבן
korban is intrinsically forbidden. יצא מוקצה yatza muktzah to exclude the sheep
that's grazing out in the wilderness that was מוקצה muktzah when it
came about יום טוב, Yom Tov, שאין איסור גופו גרם לו אלא
איסור דבר אחר גרם לו. she'ein issur gufo geram lo ela issur
davar acher geram lo. It's not intrinsically a problem, it's only a
problem because of שבת. Shabbos. So what big difference does it make?
If it's really forbidden, who cares if it's forbidden because it's טבל
tevel or forbidden because it's מוקצה? muktzah? Which is what the גמרא
Gemara says. ואי אמרת איסור מוקצה דאורייתא, ve'i amarta issur muktzah de'oraisa,
and if there really is a concept of מוקצה muktzah as a
biblical prohibition, מה לי איסור גופו מה לי איסור דבר אחר? mah
li issur gufo mah li issur davar acher? What difference does it
make whether it's forbidden because of טבל, tevel, forbidden for something else?
So this is a very roundabout way of showing if you can
bring a קרבן korban from something that's מוקצה, muktzah, it proves that
מוקצה muktzah is not really a biblical issue. Okay, so we will
pick up with this tomorrow to see the answer. But to remind
us, the question is we basically have said if הואיל ho'il gives
you a license to cook even not immediately לצורך היום, letzorech hayom,
it should give you a license to make a fire, which actually
is how we pretty much פסקן. pasken. So how could this ברייתא
braisa say you get lashes for making a fire that didn't have
a good purpose on יום טוב? Yom Tov? הואיל ho'il should give
you that license. So we cross out the case of fire in
the ברייתא, braisa, you won't get lashes for fire, and we're trying
to find another prohibition that you violate in terms of cooking on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. And right now we're suggesting it's מוקצה muktzah
because there's no theoretical use for מוקצה muktzah and by saying that
מוקצה muktzah is a biblical problem. But we are basically rejecting that.
Clearly מוקצה muktzah is not a biblical problem. The current evidence is
you can bring a קרבן korban from מוקצה. muktzah. You would not
be allowed to do that if it was a biblical problem. So
we will continue to see tomorrow if you can't say the problem
is מוקצה, muktzah, what is the biblical problem that you're going to
get lashes that we're going to use to replace this issue of
making a fire, which we know you really do have a license
for and you really won't get מלקות malkus on יום טוב? Yom
Tov? So what are we going to replace it with? Okay.